<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>nz.ursa.Lantern</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>
  <name>Lantern</name>
  <summary>Author Markdown slide decks with live preview</summary>
  <developer id="nz.ursa">
    <name>ursa.nz</name>
  </developer>

  <description>
    <p>
      Lantern is a small GUI for making Marp slide decks on GNOME. Edit on the
      left. See the slide render on the right. Present from the same window.
    </p>
    <p>
      It runs on Marp, so your Marp Markdown works as is. Themes, directives,
      backgrounds, fragments. Lantern handles the editor, the live preview,
      present mode, and export.
    </p>
    <p>
      A deck saves as one .lantern file. The slides, images, and fonts stay
      together. Rename it to .zip if you want to look inside.
    </p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Editor and live preview side by side, or focus on one</li>
      <li>Present full screen, or in a plain window for screen sharing</li>
      <li>Export to PDF, PowerPoint, or HTML</li>
      <li>One portable .lantern file holds the whole deck</li>
      <li>Drop in images and fonts. Lantern writes the reference for you</li>
      <li>Pick a theme or edit its CSS. Set fonts for the body, headings, and code</li>
      <li>Saves as you type. Follows the system light and dark setting</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">nz.ursa.Lantern.desktop</launchable>

  <categories>
    <category>Office</category>
    <category>Presentation</category>
    <category>TextEditor</category>
  </categories>

  <keywords>
    <keyword>markdown</keyword>
    <keyword>marp</keyword>
    <keyword>slides</keyword>
    <keyword>presentation</keyword>
    <keyword>deck</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <url type="homepage">https://forge.ursa.nz</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://ursa.nz/contact/</url>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1"/>

  <requires>
    <display_length compare="ge">720</display_length>
  </requires>
  <recommends>
    <control>keyboard</control>
    <control>pointing</control>
  </recommends>

  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#f4e5c0</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#2b3340</color>
  </branding>

  <releases>
    <release version="1.0.0" date="2026-05-23">
      <description>
        <p>
          Lantern 1.0. This release is about style. Choose a theme, edit its
          CSS, and place images with real control. The rest is polish that
          added up along the way.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Choose a Marp built-in theme, one Lantern ships (Ink or Dusk), or your own.</li>
          <li>Edit the theme CSS in your editor. Save, and the preview follows.</li>
          <li>Place an image with options that matter. Inline or background, size, split, and filters.</li>
          <li>Set the body, heading, or monospace font from the deck's own fonts.</li>
          <li>Title a deck, name its author, and reopen recent decks from the welcome screen.</li>
          <li>See your newest images first, and sort the list when you need to.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.9.0" date="2026-05-23">
      <description>
        <p>
          A big release. Decks now save as one file. Drop images and fonts
          straight in. Export and present from the same window.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Save a whole deck as one .lantern file. Slides, images, and fonts together.</li>
          <li>New Resources window. Drop in images and fonts. Insert them with a click.</li>
          <li>Export to PDF and PowerPoint. No bundled browser.</li>
          <li>Runs on Intel, AMD, and ARM machines.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.0" date="2026-05-19">
      <description>
        <p>First cut: editor, preview, autosave, light/dark, layout toggle.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
